Jedediah Hotchkiss Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Writings File, circa 1846-1899 (Box 48-60, Reel 44-51)
  - Books by Hotchkiss (Box 48, Reel 44)
    - The Battle-Fields of Virginia. Chancellorsville... (1866), unbound printed copy
    - Virginia, A Geographical and Political Summary (1876)
      - Printed copy
      - Drafts and notes
    - Hotchkiss' Geography of Virginia (1877) (Box 49, Reel 44)
      - Printed copies, bound and unbound
      - Notes, maps, and tracings (Box 49, Reel 45)
    - Geography of Virginia, a Supplement to the Eclectic Series of Geographies (1878)
      - Printed copy and revisions with author's emendations
      - Sketches and clippings
    - Virginia, Vol. 3 of Confederate Military History (1899) (Box 50, Reel 45)
      - Printed copy
      - Letterpress copy (Box 51, Reel 46)
      - Guidelines and contracts (Box 50, Reel 47)
      - Outlines
      - Notes (1 of 5) (Box 51, Reel 47)
      - Notes (2 of 5)
      - Notes (3 of 5)
      - Notes (4 of 5)
      - Notes (5 of 5)
      - Drafts and notes (1 of 15) (Box 52, Reel 47)
      - Drafts and notes (2 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (3 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (4 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (5 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (6 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (7 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (8 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (9 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (10 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (11 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (12 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (13 of 15) (Box 52, Reel 48)
      - Drafts and notes (14 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (15 of 15)
      - Drafts and notes (1 of 14) (Box 53, Reel 48)
      - Drafts and notes (2 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (3 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (4 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (5 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (6 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (7 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (8 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (9 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (10 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (11 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (12 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (13 of 14)
      - Drafts and notes (14 of 14)
  - Other writings by Hotchkiss (Box 54, Reel 48)
    - Civil War
      - “Cedar Run and Pope's Campaign, Aug. 1862,” Lowell Institute Lectures, Boston, Mass., 1886, Feb. 18
      - Confederate Veterans Association, Washington, D.C., text of speech, 1896, May
      - Excerpts of Hotchkiss's war diaries transcribed in War of the Rebellion: A Compilation of the Official Records... (1886)
      - From Manassas to Appomattox, review by James Longstreet
      - “List of battles fought in Virginia and West Virginia, 1861-1865”
      - Notes, Civil War, 1861-1865 (1 of 4)
      - Notes, Civil War, 1861-1865 (2 of 4)
      - Notes, Civil War, 1861-1865 (3 of 4)
      - Notes, Civil War, 1861-1865 (4 of 4)
      - “Report of Operations of the 2nd Corps. A. N. Va. and of the Army of the Valley District, 1864-1865” (Box 54, Reel 49)
      - “Supplemental Report on the Operations of the Army of the Valley District, ANV, 14 Nov. 1864-12 Apr. 1865”
      - Transcripts, miscellaneous Civil War papers (1 of 3) (Box 55, Reel 49)
      - Transcripts, miscellaneous Civil War papers (2 of 3)
      - Transcripts, miscellaneous Civil War papers (3 of 3)
      - Transcripts, miscellaneous Civil War papers (1 of 2) (Box 56, Reel 49)
      - Transcripts, miscellaneous Civil War papers (2 of 2)
      - “War Papers Digest of General Orders and Letters of General T. J. Jackson, 1861-1863” (Box 57, Reel 49)
    - Education
      - Lecture notebooks and class rolls
      - Lecture notes (Box 57, Reel 49)
        - 1847-1848
        - circa 1850-1859
        - circa 1854-1855 (Box 57, Reel 50)
        - circa 1865-1890
        - Miscellanous
      - Mathematics notes
      - Speech texts, circa 1852-1856
      - Sunday School lecture notes, class rolls, and miscellaneous notes
        - 1860
        - 1894-1895
    - Geography, land surveying, lumbering, and mining (Box 58, Reel 50)
      - “The Coal Fields of West Virginia,” circa 1894
      - “Corner trees” study, 1894
      - “A Description of the Elizabeth Furnace Iron Property,” 1867
      - “Essay on the Water Courses of Augusta County, Virginia,” undated
      - Extract from Mineral Resources of the United States, p. 307 (1885)
      - “The Great Flat-Top Coal Field of Virginia and a Decade of Its Development,” circa 1893
      - “History of Mapmaking,” circa 1873
      - “Localities of Indian Mounds in the Shenandoah Valley,” undated
      - “The Royal Land Company of Virginia,” 1877
      - “Virginia,” Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1888
      - The Virginias, with notes, 1886 (1 of 2)
      - The Virginias, with notes, 1886 (2 of 2)
      - The Virginias Railway, 1896
    - Miscellaneous subjects (Box 58, Reel 51)
      - Essay on the Bill for the Encouragement of Immigration, 1873
      - “The Tuscarora Indians,” 1894
      - Verse and other writings, circa 1846-1860
  - Writings by others (Box 59, Reel 51)
    - Adams, William H.
    - Agassiz, Louis
    - Allan, William
    - Bigelow, John
    - Allan, William
    - Blackford, Charles M.
    - Boswell, James K.
    - Buck, William B. (1 of 2)
    - Buck, William B. (2 of 2)
    - Callender, Bessie
    - Clews, Henry
    - Evans, Charles A.
    - Doyle, Thomas S.
    - Grinnan, A. G.
    - Heinrich, Oswald J. (Box 60, Reel 51)
    - Henderson, G. F. R. (1 of 2)
    - Henderson, G. F. R. (2 of 2)
    - Hunt, T. Sterry
    - Jacobs, Prof.
    - Johnson, Bradley T.
    - McGuire, Hunter (1 of 3)
    - McGuire, Hunter (2 of 3)
    - McGuire, Hunter (3 of 3)
    - Robertson, Frank A.
    - Royall, W. S. (Box 60, Reel 52)
    - Slaughter, Philip
    - Steinwehr, A. von and D. G. Brinton
    - Stiles, Robert
    - Strout, Newton A.
    - Waddell, J. Addison
- Miscellany, circa 1846-1908 (Box 61-74, Reel 52-61)
  Scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, genealogical and autobiographical material, financial records, printed matter, and legal papers.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and thereunder by subject or chronologically.
  - Civil War papers (Box 61, Reel 52)
    - Invoices of engineer property and quartermaster reports, 1862-1863
    - Provision returns, 5th Regiment, Virginia Infantry, 1861
    - Appropriations and invoices for engineer property, 1865
    - Morning reports and returns, 1862
    - General orders, 1862-1864
    - Confederate scrip, Augusta County, Va., 1862-1863
    - Invitations, passes, and memberships in organizations, 1868, 1888-1898 (1 of 2)
    - Invitations, passes, and memberships in organizations, 1868, 1888-1898 (2 of 2)
  - Financial papers, 1846-1908 (Box 61, Reel 52)
    - Account books and property inventory, 1846
    - Account books (Box 61, Reel 53)
      - 1853-1896
      - 1853-1857, 1897-1898
      - 1865
      - 1868-1875, 1898
      - 1878-1884 (Box 62, Reel 53)
      - 1887
      - 1888-1893
      - 1890-1895
    - Canceled checks and stubs
      - 1878
      - 1880-1881
      - 1881-1882
      - 1883
      - 1884 (Box 62, Reel 54)
      - 1885-1887
      - 1888-1889 (Box 63, Reel 54)
      - 1888-1893
      - 1890-1892
      - 1892-1898
      - 1893 (Box 64, Reel 55)
      - 1894
      - 1895
      - 1896
      - 1897
      - 1898
      - 1881, 1890-1891
    - Bank notes (Box 65, Reel 55)
      - 1859, 1869
      - 1870-1878
      - 1880-1888
      - 1889
      - 1890-1894
      - 1895-1899
    - Receipts and bills
      - 1850-1859
      - 1860-1865
      - 1866-1869 (Box 65, Reel 56)
      - 1870-1879
      - 1880-1882
      - 1883-1885
      - 1886-1889
      - 1890-1891 (Box 66, Reel 56)
      - 1892-1894
      - 1895-1896 (Box 66, Reel 57)
      - 1897-1898, undated
  - Financial papers, Sara Anne Comfort Hotchkiss (Box 66)
    - Account books
      - 1896-1900
      - 1901-1903
      - 1902-1903, undated
      - 1904-1905 (Box 67)
      - 1905-1906
    - Canceled checks and stubs
      - 1899
      - 1902-1903
      - 1904
      - 1905-1906
      - 1907-1908
    - Receipts and bills (Box 68)
      - 1898
      - 1899
      - 1900
      - 1901-1902
      - 1903
      - 1904
      - 1905
      - 1906
      - 1907 (1 of 2)
      - 1907 (2 of 2)
      - 1908
  - Genealogical and biographical files (Box 69, Reel 57)
    - Hotchkiss genealogy
    - “Hotchkiss Family and Relations...”
    - Correspondence concerning Hotchkiss genealogy, 1876-1901
    - Genealogy
      - Notes and printed material
      - Newspaper clippings
    - “For the Major...” (poem)
    - Parole papers and oath of allegiance, 1865
    - Appointment as topographer, Office of the Publication of Records of the Rebellion, 1893
    - Resolutions, eulogies upon the death of Hotchkiss
    - Autobiographical memoranda and addenda by Sara Anne Comfort Hotchkiss
  - Legal papers
    - Summons
    - Land transactions
    - Mapping contracts and copyrights
    - Miscellaneous legal transactions, court decisions (1 of 2) (Box 69, Reel 58)
    - Miscellaneous legal transactions, court decisions (2 of 2)
    - Property valuation, taxes, 1894
    - Stocks and bonds
    - Mossy Creek Academy and Loch Willow School, Virginia, circa 1853-1860
    - Insurance papers
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1855-1899 (Box 70, Reel 58)
    - Antietam, Md.
    - Appomattox, Va.
    - Cedar Mountain, Va.
    - Chancellorsville, Va.
    - Coal production
    - Confederate veterans
    - Dabney, Robert L.
    - Davis, Jefferson
    - Early, Jubal A.
    - Fredericksburg, Va.
    - Gaines Mill, Va.
    - Gettysburg, Pa.
    - Hotchkiss, Jedediah
      - Obituaries and biographical
      - Virginia politics
      - Lectures (1 of 2)
      - Lectures (2 of 2)
      - Book reviews
    - Jackson, Stonewall (1 of 2)
    - Jackson, Stonewall (2 of 2)
    - Jackson, Stonewall, staff officers (Box 71, Reel 59)
    - Kernstown, Va.
    - Lee, Fitzhugh
    - Lee, Robert E.
    - Lincoln, Abraham, assassination of
    - Longstreet, James
    - McDowell, Battle of
    - Manassas, 1st Battle of
    - Mosby, John S.
    - New Market, Battle of
    - Pelham, John
    - Petersburg, Battle of
    - Piedmont, Battle of
    - Shenandoah Valley Campaign, 1864
    - Sheridan, Philip Henry
    - Spanish-American War
    - Spottsylvania Court House, Battle of
    - Stuart, Jeb
    - Virginia
      - Early Virginia history
      - Virginia Civil War regiments
      - Virginia and the Civil War
      - Staunton, Va.
      - Geography and natural resources
    - West Virginia
    - World's Columbian Exposition, Chicago, Ill., 1893
    - World's Industrial and Cotton Centennial Exposition, New Orleans, La., 1884
    - Miscellaneous subjects
      - Pre-Civil War
      - Civil War
        - Casualties and strengths of both sides
        - Confederate officers, A-W
        - Naval engagements
        - Prisoner-of-war camps
        - Richmond Dispatch, 1895, Dec. 1-1898, Oct. 8
      - Post Civil War (1 of 3) (Box 72, Reel 59)
      - Post Civil War (2 of 3)
      - Post Civil War (3 of 3)
  - Printed matter
    - Notices of meetings and lectures
    - Train schedules (Box 72, Reel 60)
    - “Constitution and By Laws...Sons of Temperance, Mossy Creek, Virginia,” 1849
    - Pamphlets
    - Cartoons, “Jeff Davis Mess, 1861,” blueprint
    - Davis, Jefferson, bail bond, 1867
    - Miscellany (1 of 5) (Box 73, Reel 60)
    - Miscellany (2 of 5)
    - Miscellany (3 of 5)
    - Miscellany (4 of 5)
    - Miscellany (5 of 5)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Mossy Creek Academy, Augusta County, Va., catalogs with clippings, circa 1853-1860
    - Miscellaneous (Box 74, Reel 61)
      - circa 1868-1877
      - circa 1869-1870
    - Virginia schools, circa 1871
    - Newspaper items concerning Stonewall Jackson Camp, United Confederate Veterans, Staunton, Va., 1893
    - John W. Daniel on Earl's Campaign and Hunter McGuire on Stonewall Jackson, 1894
    - Politics, 1896